<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A beame of light darted thorough [sic] the clouds, or, Truth breaking forth from under a veil by Joshua Miller.</title>
            <author>Miller, Joshua, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2062</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35047</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14960510</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14960510</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102989</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50858)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102989)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1575:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A beame of light darted thorough [sic] the clouds, or, Truth breaking forth from under a veil by Joshua Miller.</title>
                  <author>Miller, Joshua, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 63 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H.C. and L.L.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Apocalyptic literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102989:1"/>
            <p>A BEAME OF LIGHT DARTED Thorough the Clouds: OR, <hi>Truth breaking forth from under a Veil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Joſhua Miller.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ZACH. 14.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>But it ſhall come to paſſe, that at the evening time it ſhall be light.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. C.</hi> and <hi>L. L.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:102989:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102989:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Honourable, the Commiſsioners for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Glamorgan.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I obſerve the viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes and changes God makes upon the world, it puts me to a ſtand how to call men honourable.</p>
            <p>But conſidering the noble Titles that God himſelf gives to men in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6. as, <hi>I have ſaid, ye are Gods,</hi> having the moſt ancient Author, I ſhall not erre to call you Honourable.</p>
            <p>This laſt age is a time wherein Truth is much increaſed, arid much contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and that glorious liberty Truth brings in is much abuſed by miſ-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>And indeed the miſt is yet ſo great which makes moſt men ſtumble, for
<pb facs="tcp:102989:3"/>want of day-light; yet our good God hath promiſed, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 30 26. <hi>That the light of the Sun ſhall be ſevenfold,</hi> and ſuch as will not ſee, ſhall ſee, and be aſhamed: I have more then ordinary ground to believe your zealous affection to Truth, which works in me a boldneſſe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent this ſmall Book to your view: it is but a bloſſome of the tree of life, which may prove ſweet to the taſt, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to the eye, if divinely underſtood; for I judge your minds like to that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpeech of <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>It became a noble mind as well to accept ſmall things from others, as to give great things to them:</hi> Nay, God himſelfe gives the greateſt good to man, and accepts the ſmalleſt returnes from them; ſo I truſt the ſmalleſt volume may be read by you as well as the greateſt.</p>
            <p>Yet would I not uſe your names for Patronage, not accounting any Booke worth a Patron, which hath not Truth to patronize it, which if this had not,
<pb facs="tcp:102989:3"/>I ſhould be as unwilling to ſet your names as my owne before it; but knowing you are as deſirous to know Truth, as my ſelfe to ſearch after it, you will do well to follow the wiſe Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans, to try all things.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe, when I duly ponder how all Writings in this Age are gloſſed upon, by the opinionative phanſies of men, moſt ſpeaking not as this Truth requires, nor yet as the Author meaneth, I then had ſome thoughts to have kept theſe things in my breaſt, where they firſt burned, rather then ſend them abroad to be deſcanted upon by mans judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>But finding the fire to kindle, it muſt breake forth; and having greater arguments from the Author of Truth, then its controverter, knowing that no Truth is the worſe becauſe men diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reliſh it; and from that ſweet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and delight I had then in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it, I thought it better to lay
<pb facs="tcp:102989:4"/>my ſelfe open to any cenſure, then to conceale any thing which may (by the Divine Power) conduce to the caſting downe of darkneſſe in its Principles.</p>
            <p>As for that Truſt God hath now after ſo many conteſts, put into your hands, you will do well in all your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, to looke up unto the Author of this Honour, and the end for which he hath thus exalted you; and if you act according to his directions, which is for truth, righteouſneſſe and a juſt liberty, as I have great hopes God hath now given you this Power for this end, that thoſe poor dark Countreys where the light of our good God hath not yet ſhined, that you may be reſtorers of paths to dwell in, furtherers of the Goſpell, and in doing theſe things God may fulfill that promiſe to us by you, as to be Nurſing-Fathers to theſe Orphan-like Countreyes: and me-thinks I ſee God pointing out glorious things by you,
<pb facs="tcp:102989:4"/>in being active men, for good: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore joyne hand and heart together, forget, all ſelfe-injuries, or other miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes.</p>
            <p>And truly then I may boldly ſay to you, even to you, without any flattery, that your Honour will be more then a bare Title, it will be emblazon'd in the divine Heraldrie, where your names in no Age ſhall be rooted out, for ſuch is the memory of the juſt.</p>
            <p>I need not tell you how God in theſe eight yeares laſt paſt hath out of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe brought ſtrength, made thoſe things that are not to confound thoſe that are, and now he goes [<hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.2.] <hi>out of the mouth of babes and ſucklings</hi> to ſhew forth his praiſe; you have ſeen this in ſome meaſure already, the ſame God that opens and no man ſhuts, keep open your eyes ſtill, leaſt any among you be found to deſpiſe the day of ſmall things; how my indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours,
<pb facs="tcp:102989:5"/>or rather the Lords leading me in the making knowne thoſe Truths: how they will ſpeed amongſt others, I know not.</p>
            <p>Yet it will be a comfort to me to hear that you bid them welcome.</p>
            <p>For, I have learnt not to eſteem truth the leſſe, becauſe frowned upon, nor the greater, if ſmiled on; but here is my joy and glory, to ſee the Truth of God held forth in the world, whether it be received or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected.</p>
            <p>I feare I have troubled you with too large an Epiſtle to ſo ſmall a Book, but conſider that Love writ it, and ſo read it.</p>
            <p>I beg from my heart, that as you are honourable, ſo you may be kept hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and muſt from the love of God tell you plainly, that I rather deſire you may loſe your Honor, then loſe or want hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, which (in ſome reſpect) is the Crown of bleſſings.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:102989:5"/>
Yet in every ſtate I ſhall ſooner for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get my owne name, then not remember my ſelf to be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your reall Servant ready in any work of God, <hi>Joſhua Miller.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:102989:6"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>KInd Reader, the deſire I have that truth may be impartially underſtood, makes me to requeſt thee impartially to read this ſmall Book: what thou findeſt in it hath the face of Chriſt, account it fair, beautifull, and be in love with it: what ever my delight and gaine hath been in knowing, writing it, I wiſh thee as much in reading; if the golden key of the divine Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit go along and open what may ſeem hard to thee, then make no queſtion, but it will be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable: if thou findeſt any thing opened that hath in many books been left under a veile, give God the glory; if thou findest any error, conſider that the Writer, Reader, and Printer hath many; yet I know none in the booke, excepting the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes of the Primer, which I pray the candidly to correct, and let me have thy love, though I cannot have thy mind in all things: However I muſt alwayes from the law of Love, continue thine in all Christian ſervice.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joſhua Miller.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:102989:6"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> I.</label> WHat a Saint Practicall is.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> II.</label> Whether Repentance pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede Faith, and which is firſt to be preached.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> III.</label> What Prayer is.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> IV.</label> Whether a juſtified perſon ought to pray for the pardon of ſin.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> V.</label> Whether this viſible world ſhall be deſtroyed or changed, and how.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> VI.</label> Whether all creatures ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to a ſtate of perfection.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> VII.</label> What may be ſaid of the time of this change.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> VIII.</label> What ſure ground we have to believe this change is nigh, and that many things muſt firſt come to paſſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> IX.</label> Whether we may not expect a glorious reſt before the finall appearing, and what reſt it will be.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> X.</label> A taſte of divine joy, and what it is.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:102989:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102989:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> What a Saint Practicall is.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Nowledge of the Myſteries and hidden Properties of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall things, is for the moſt part the ſtudy and delight of the earthly man. Knowledge of the divine and glorious Myſteries of God in the Goſpell, is the ſtudy and delight of the holy and heavenly man.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Venning</hi> in ingenuous and godly man, hath of late in a ſmall book of his, ſet forth a Saint in the Theoreticall and Practicall Part, in ſeeming contradictions, yet very lively and truly.</p>
            <p>I ſhall caſt in my Mite into this Treaſury, though it be not worth the looking on; yet it may challenge to be of the ſame coin, though ſmall.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He dwells in love, and love dwells in him, he loves all that bear his Fathers Image, a ſpark or a flame; where he beholds his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſtamp, he receives the perſon, he that loveth not his brother, abideth in darkneſſe, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.11.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:102989:8"/>
2. He is more inwardly holy, then out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly holy, he had rather be that which he ſeems not to be, then ſeem to be what he is not; he deſires not the face of <hi>Ianus,</hi> but the heart of <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. He abſtaines from evill, not becauſe men may ſee him, but God; he ſpeaks like <hi>Ioſeph, Gen.</hi> 39.9. <hi>How can I do this great wickedneſſe, and ſin againſt God?</hi> The ſight of God is more in his eye to affect him, then the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſin is to allure him: As I remember a Monk being tempted to Adultery, the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot brought him into a ſecret place, and told him none could ſee them there: He anſwers her, who is God? is he nothing? bring me to a place where God ſeeth not, and I will commit it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He eſtimates himſelfe the leaſt of all Saints, as <hi>Iohn,</hi> I am but a voice and no more, <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.3. he prefers all men before him, yet he aſpires to live above the higheſt Saint, he would be more holy then they, and yet more humble.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He walks ſo exactly as if there was no Goſpell, yet he dies ſo comfortably, as if there was nothing but Goſpell. Or thus, he ſo ſtrictly lives, as if he were to be ſaved by his own works, yet dies, as if there was no Law, his language is <hi>Pauls, Phil.</hi> 3.14
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102989:8"/>
               <hi>I preſſe forward toward the marke,</hi> as men run in a race, ſtriving for the maſtery, ſo doth he.</p>
            <p n="6">6. He is never ſatisfied with grace, but ſoon filled with the world, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.34. <hi>Lord, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermore give us this bread,</hi> not now and then, but alwayes, he knowes there is more in God then can be deſired, and yet he deſires more then he can attain to.</p>
            <p>Lord, feed me with the crums that fall from thy table, rather then let me want, if I may not taſt the fineſt of the wheat, let me have the courſer, ſo it be bread it will nouriſh me: <hi>Davids</hi> language is his, <hi>As the Hart pants after the water brooks, ſo doth my ſoule after the living God;</hi> not a dead letter, but a quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſpirit, not the title or term of a God, but the living Lord: nothing below himſelf will ſerve his turne; unleſſe I injoy God in all, I want every thing.</p>
            <p n="7">7. He is more afraid of ſin then hell; for he knowes, where ſin reigns not, hell hath no dominion; and yet he can ſay, [1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55.] <hi>O death where is thy ſting?</hi> Death came in by ſin, take the cauſe away, and the effect will ceaſe.</p>
            <p n="8">8. He reſpects Gods glory more then his owne profit, and he will pluck out his right eye and cut off his right hand, rather then God ſhall be diſhonoured, nothing is dearer
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102989:9"/>to me, then him who makes me deare to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. to ſuch as believe he is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, or honourable.</p>
            <p n="9">9. He is more afraid he ſhall not ſuffer for Chriſt, then afraid to ſuffer for him; I muſt, ſaith a gracious heart, tread his ſteps, follow him to his foot, injoy the Croſſe, and then I ſhall know how to weare the Crowne: we muſt fill up the meaſure of his ſufferings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind in the body; gold is not pure, till it be fire-proof, all things muſt be tried by fire, I count all things but loſſe and dung, or dogs meat, not worth the looking on: my owne righteouſneſſe muſt be burnt up, that where in I formerly boaſted, muſt now ſuffer loſſe, I am ready not to be bound only, but to die at Jeruſalem for the Name of the Lord Jeſus; ſelf and legall righteouſneſſe would pull me back from this ſuffering, but die I muſt to all ſuch carnall intereſts; I am to be loſt to the fleſh, that I may be found in the ſpirit as for outward ſufferings he expects them alſo, the aſhes of holy men are the beſt compoſt to manure the Church; if I die in fire, God will make me out of the aſhes; he ſaith to dry bones, live.</p>
            <p n="10">10. He loves all truth, for the Authors ſake, not for him that ſpeaks it. that truth which ſtrikes at his ſin, as well as that which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102989:9"/>ſhewes him a Saviour; Lord lead me into all truth, cut out my dead fleſh, let not ſin rule over me; rebuke them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſharply</hi> (or cuttingly) <hi>that they may be found in the Faith, Tit.</hi> 1.3. if God doth wound him, he knowes it is for his good.</p>
            <p n="11">11. He counts the higheſt life in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be the greateſt death, and knowes he can never live well untill he be out of the world, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.96. <hi>I have ſeen an end of all perfection;</hi> in ſeeing one thing in the world he hath ſeen all; for all in the world is but the ſame earth appearing in various formes and figures, the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to him is but as the track of a ſhip at Sea, ſoon made and ſoon marr'd, all its beauty is but skin-deep, 'tis a <hi>Tohu</hi> and <hi>Bohu</hi> in a comely garb.</p>
            <p n="12">12. He prayes more to have ſin cured, then to have it covered; Lord take away my ſin ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the affliction, leave no ſore unhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, though I ſuffer by it, yet I would have no ſore left running, leaſt the dogs of this world feed upon me, I would not be meat for ſuch cormorants, as <hi>Paul</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.8.) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought the Lord thrice againſt his temptation, ſo doth he, he ſeeks to weare out ſin by his warring againſt it.</p>
            <p n="13">13. He knowes his happineſſe conſiſts not in knowing the nature of God, but in being
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102989:10"/>made partaker of the Divine Nature, a bare knowing God to be, cannot make me to be; ſuch as are joyned to the Lord are one ſpirit, 'tis ſpirit-work to know God, I muſt be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine as well as ſpeak ſo, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3. <hi>If ye have taſted that the Lord is gracious;</hi> the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, gracious, notes ſweet, profitable, taſt makes judgement, I muſt taſt God to be good, ſweet, gracious, and then I ſhall act and ſpeak divinely.</p>
            <p n="14">14. No grief goes ſo neare his heart, as his grievous ſtrayings from the life of God; he holds it as neceſſary in ſome reſpect to ſorrow for ſin, as to joy in God: they that ſowe in tears ſhall reap in joy, there muſt be a ſeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time before a harveſt; as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks, ſo doth he, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.4. <hi>Againſt thee, thee onely have I ſinned:</hi> that which aggravates an evill is that it's committed againſt love, <hi>Peter</hi> thus went out, and wept bitterly, <hi>Semper Lachrymis ſuffuſos habuiſſe oculos;</hi> ſome obſerve that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver after <hi>Peter</hi> had his checks furrowed with continuall tears: relapſe into ſin makes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenting.</p>
            <p n="15">15. He receives ſtrikings as well as ſtrokings with patience and thankfulneſſe; a true ſon of <hi>Job, the Lord gives, and the Lord takes away, bleſſed be his Name,</hi> not <hi>curſe God, and die,</hi> as the woman counſelled him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:102989:10"/>
This effeminate woman the world is mans Tempter to miſcall his Maker, look on God ſaith ſhe, he afflicts thee to deſtroy thee, he will damne thee at laſt; a gracious heart anſwers, thou ſpeakeſt like a fooliſh woman, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>I know all things worke for my good,</hi> frownes as well as ſmiles, whatever is called good, or whatever is called evill; God brings light out of darkneſſe, unity out of diſparity; as God ſpeaks, ſo doth he, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 54.17. <hi>No weapon formed againſt me ſhall proſper:</hi> the true proſperity of a thing is in its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, but all things againſt me ſhall have a change, therefore not proſper: he ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choes to <hi>David,</hi> it's good for me that I was afflicted, affliction in Gods Schoole makes us proficients.</p>
            <p>The more you beat the wallnut-tree, the more it bears; ſo the Saints gaine by loſſes, after ſuch an afflicton, ſuch a mercy I had: contraries fruſtrate one another, life doth death, joy doth ſorrow, affliction firſt comes, and ploughs up the fallow ground of my heart, then is the ſeed ſowne; he ſpeaks not as that wicked King, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 6.33. <hi>This evill is of the Lord, why ſhould I wait any longer?</hi> but rather, what evill in me brought this? true and juſt are all thy Judgements, O Lord God.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:102989:11"/>
16. He ſees nothing of the fleſh dwelling in another, but asks at home, Is not this evill in me? As <hi>Plato,</hi> when he ſaw any one dumb in the ſtreet, would ſpeak to himſelf, <hi>Num e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go talis?</hi> Am not I ſuch a one? the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward any thing is, the more ſtrong, whether it be good or evill; ſin is moſt aggravated by a ſuppoſing ſecreſie, he makes inquiry as the Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.22. <hi>Maſter, is it I?</hi> He loves to ask, though he be not guilty.</p>
            <p n="17">17. He is as holy in his Cloſet as in the Church, when from the Saints, as well as with them; in all his walkings he is as <hi>light in the world, Mat.</hi> 5.16. no ſociety of men can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh his fellowſhip with God.</p>
            <p n="18">18. He ſo purſues holineſſe, as if he held free-will; yet he prayes for it, as if he had power to do nothing, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. We are not ſufficient of our ſelves to thinke one good thought, man cannot work in Gods Myſtery, 'tis an Art, which all the Maſters of Art are yet but punies in this School, divine leſſons are weightier, harder and higher then their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity Lectures.</p>
            <p n="19">19. He counts no ſin ſmall, but believes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſin hath weight enough to weigh him to death; if he diſcern a mote in his brothers eye, he thinks there is a beame in his owne; he had rather make ſin more then it is by ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102989:11"/>then ſeek to make it leſſe; for he that hideth his ſin ſhall not proſper.</p>
            <p n="20">20. He is more zealous for power then forme, he had rather leave undone ſmaller matters, then neglect the weighty things of the Law; righteouſneſſe, juſtice, truth, theſe have Gods proper ſtamp upon them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be moſt looked after.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome cleare demonſtrations of a practicall Chriſtian, for there are many falſe Chriſtians now gone out in the world.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Whether Repentance precede Faith, and which is firſt to be preached.</head>
            <p>GOD in this laſt age is making out his truth in plainneſſe, whereas in former ages it hath been much clouded; therefore marvell not, if thou readeſt that which will be gain-ſayed.</p>
            <p>It hath been a great diſpute amongſt men, whether Repentance go before Faith, or Faith Repentance? I ſhall not erre againſt truth, nor yet diſagree from ſome men, to ſay that Faith is alway before Repentance in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of a Sinner to God; and if this be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102989:12"/>true, then it will neceſſarily follow, that Faith ought to be preached before Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>For, I judge Faith to be the inſtrumentall cauſe of Repentance, and not Repentance the cauſe of Faith: It is true, that in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of a ſinner to God, Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance ever go together; yet Faith is the firſt-borne, and may challenge the right hand of fellowſhip.</p>
            <p>Now the difficulty ſeems to be opened in this particular: It is very true, that Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is (for the moſt part) diſcovered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Faith to men, therefore men judge that Repentance is, and muſt be before Faith.</p>
            <p>I anſwer: Firſt, that it will not follow alwayes true, that the firſt in appearance, is firſt in the ſoul; Faith I compare to the ſeed caſt in the ground, Repentance I call the blade ſprung up from that ſeed: Now no man will judge ſo weakly, that becauſe he ſeeth the blade firſt ſpring up, therefore the ſeed is not there.</p>
            <p>Againe, you may underſtand it by this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion; when a candle is lighted in a room, and I come into that room, true it is, I have the light firſt in my eye, and ſee that firſt, yet the candle was there before the light was; ſo it is often true, that repentance is firſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, but not firſt wrought.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:102989:12"/>
Conſider ſecondly, that if Repentance be before Faith, then I ask, what doth that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance avail man? If that place be true, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. <hi>Without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God?</hi> I may then ſafely conclude, if Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is firſt, why was not <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> their repentance accepted? was it not for want of true Faith? I never found in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that any did truly repent before faith; <hi>Job</hi> in his laſt Chapter when he had ſeen the Lord he abhorres himſelfe; <hi>Iſai.</hi> 6.5. ſo <hi>Iſaiah</hi> when he had ſeen the Lord, he cries, <hi>Woe is me, I am undone;</hi> ſo that generall promiſe runs, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. <hi>They ſhall look upon him whom they have pierced and mourn for him:</hi> all implies a ſeeing before ſorrow.</p>
            <p>I put the caſe thus: Suppoſe a man ſhould meet with his friend, but diſguiſed, and ſo ſhould take him for his enemie, and kill him; now when his vizard is taken off, and he finds that it was his dear friend, what think you, will not ſorrow follow? ſo untill a ſoule come to apprehend that againſt his Saviour, his Father and Friend, he hath wounded him that loves him, when he ſeeth this, he will ſorrow kindly indeed.</p>
            <p>For a man will never be willing to account his own ſtate bad, untill he is brought into a beliefe of a better ſtate in Chriſt for him;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102989:13"/>
               <hi>Peter,</hi> who was a Diſciple of Chriſt, could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have repented of his ſin in denying his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, if he had not looked upon him; much leſs is a ſinner able to repent of his ſins, but from a ſaving ſight of God in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now this being undeniably true, then faith in Chriſt muſt be firſt preached: And herein I know, many godly men in their preaching go againſt their own principles, who all ſay, that repentance without faith is dead, yet they preach repentance firſt, and qualifications; a man muſt be ſo and ſo humbled, before he muſt lay hold upon Chriſt: and by this means many poor ſouls are kept under the hatches, dare not lay hold upon Chriſt, untill ſo far humbled; I my ſelf having repentance, being kept four years under this law, and thought it preſumption in me to believe my ſins pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, untill qualified. Truly I muſt judg this to be a branch of Purgatory, and meerly legall, where men put knots upon a truth, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be nakedly diſcovered to ſinners on earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But an Objection may ariſe: Did not Chriſt in his firſt Sermon on the mount preach repentance when he ſaid, <hi>Repent, for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven is at hand? Mat.</hi> 4.17. Did not <hi>John</hi> alſo preach the ſame doctrine? <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.4. ſo did not <hi>Peter</hi> preach the ſame, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19: <hi>Repent, that your ſins may be blotted out?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:102989:13"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, that it is true, Chriſt did ſo; but note, it was before the Goſpell was come; <hi>Repent, for the kingdom of heaven is at hand,</hi> preſently to follow upon it; and the word (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>repent</hi> here ſignifies a change of the mind onely: Chriſt he was a fulfiller of the Law, and ſpoke many things as in that relation: and this doctrine was ſuited to the Phariſes, who thought all was well; Chriſt tells them, they muſt be of another mind, or els no ſalvation; they muſt have another kind of faith then what they already had: Now here men miſtake, who take repentance in the latitude of it, and ſo ſuppoſe humiliation and ſorrow muſt firſt be, before faith. I would ask any ſoul that had true repentance, this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, When they were in a ſtate of ſorrow for ſins? What made them thus ſorrow? Was it not firſt becauſe they had offended a loving Father? Or ſecondly, had they no ſecret hope in them that Chriſt would be merciful, though at preſent they durſt not lay hold upon him? why did they ſorrow els, if they had no dram of faith they ſhould be ſaved, their tears were then ſpent in vain. I am confident, never any man was yet converted, but he had the ſparks of faith, though not flaming. Therefore I may ſafely conclude, that for any man to preach repentance before faith, is not to preach the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102989:14"/>Goſpell, but the Law: And further, if they own the title of Miniſters of the Goſpel, why then they ſhould obey his generall command, <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.l5, 16. <hi>Go ye and preach the Goſpell, he that believes ſhall be ſaved, he that believes not ſhall be damned:</hi> Surely if Repentance muſt firſt be preached, then why ſhould Chriſt exclude it in this great command? I know not who can teach his Maſter, and if the word (<hi>Goſpell</hi>) ſignifies glad tidings, as all men judge, I wonder in the order of the Goſpell wherein ſhould the Goſpell excell the Law, if it bids men firſt repent, and then believe? this is no good newes, to tell me I muſt firſt repent, be humbled for ray ſinnes, the Law ſpeaks this of it ſelf, ſuch a kind of preaching is as if I ſhould firſt put out a mans eyes, and then bid him look upon me.</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Object.</hi> But ſome may object, What is the meaning of that place in <hi>Acts</hi> 20.21. where <hi>Paul</hi> testified to the <hi>Jews and Greeks repentance towards God, and faith towards our Lord Jeſus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer: That true it is, in the converſion of a ſinner to God Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance ever go together; yet Faith is firſt in order of nature in the ſoule: and for that place of repentance towards God, I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not that it muſt be preached or wrought, but <hi>Paul</hi> here onely diſtinguiſheth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102989:14"/>the objects of Faith and Repentance; God conſidered abſolutely in himſelfe, is the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whom we have offended, or diſobeyed, repentance muſt be in reſpect of him; God came in Chriſt reconciling the world to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſo under this notion there muſt be faith upon Chriſt; ſo that this Scripture makes nothing as to the order of faith &amp; repentance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Object.</hi> But doth not <hi>Paul</hi> ſay before faith came we was kept under a Schoolmaſter, and the <hi>Law was our Schoolmaſter to bring us to Christ? Gal.</hi> 3.24. Doth not that humble us for Chriſt? and if ſo, then we are to be quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in ſome ſenſe before we believe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer: That <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith the Law was, he ſpeaks of it as in the time paſt, that is to ſay, before Chriſt came the Law was a Schoolemaſter, and we were ever learning, but never able to be proficients by it; but it was but untill faith came, there faith is taken <hi>objectivè,</hi> for the object of faith: we were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the dominion and killing power of the Law, not that it can prepare us for Chriſt, for then Chriſt could not be a perfect Saviour: And although moſt men interpret it by allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to a Schoolemaſter, who fits Schollers for the Univerſity, ſo (ſay they) the Law is a Schoolmaſter to prepare men.</p>
            <p>For my pare, I rather with ſubmiſſion to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102989:15"/>the unbiaſſed judgment, ſuppoſe the word [Schoolemaſter,] rather notes this, that the Law had the maſterſhip and rule over us, and we was ſubject to what it threatned; but when Chriſt came this Schoolmaſter had us not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his bonds and puniſhments, as if by it we could be taught everlaſting life; and as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Call no man your Maſter, but one even Chriſt:</hi> ſo that the Law cannot be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in this ſenſe, that it prepares us for Chriſt, unleſſe this preparation be meant that it leaves us under condemnation; <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. <hi>For by the Law is the knowledge of ſin,</hi> yet not an efficacious knowledge of ſinne, ſo as to ſhew us a Saviour, but it will cauſe us to run from him.</p>
            <p>And indeed take a man ſimply conſidered, as obeying the Law, he never cares for a Saviour, thinks he is well enough, as the practiſes of the Phariſees teſtifie fully to us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Object.</hi> But how are thoſe promiſes true, where God calls (<hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28.) <hi>ſuch as are weary and heavy laden,</hi> and <hi>I dwell with him that is of a humble and contrite ſpirit,</hi> and <hi>the whole have no need of the Phyſitian, but they which are ſick?</hi> Muſt not men firſt be qualified before God call them?</p>
            <p n="3">3.<hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer: Firſt, theſe places do not demonſtrate that every man muſt be ſo before
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102989:15"/>faith, but only declares, that it is poſſible men are, and may be by the Law ſo terrified for ſin: yet this alſo is by the ſpirit, altough they may have terror, yet this cannot be true humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but a legall afrightment for ſin: Theſe promiſes are only to teſtifie Gods bowells of compaſſion to ſuch as well as others, and from his mercy calls them to believe in him, mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as I candidly interpret it, that unleſſe God calls them, they wil ſtil be mourning, and think they are not qualified ſufficiently for him; and therfore God manifeſts his love towards them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Anſ.</hi> But ſecondly, I anſwer, if the Goſpell muſt be preached only to ſuch upon conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then I ask how can it be a free Goſpell? which notes it comes without any ſuch condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be performed by us. And further, how can a man follow Chriſts command to preach the Goſpell to every creature, if qualification in any ſenſe muſt go before? <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth us another leſſon, <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. <hi>This is a faithfull ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Chriſt came to ſave ſinners, of whom I am chief,</hi> he ſaith not if they are humbled, but calls to ſinners indefinitely, <hi>qua</hi> ſinners, Chriſt comes to give us faith, that we may be humbled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> But may not repentance then be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched? yea, in its proper place as a fruit of faith: I would have all that go under that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble title of Preachers of the Goſpell to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102989:16"/>conſider <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpeech to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Now then we are Embaſſadours in Chriſts ſtead, as though God did beſeech you in us: We pray you in Chriſts ſtead be ye reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to God;</hi> That is to ſay, we ſpeak in love to you, that through love you may receive and believe that teſtimony which God hath given of his Son; and what is this teſtimony, but to believe that record that God is a Father to us in Chriſt? I might mention divers other places where Faith is firſt laid down, as <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37. where <hi>Philip</hi> ſaid to the Eunuch, <hi>If thou believeſt with all thy heart thou mayest;</hi> ſo <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.29. when they asked what they ſhould do to be ſaved, why Chriſt anſwers, <hi>This is the work of God, that you believe on him whom he hath ſent:</hi> To end this queſtion with that place in <hi>Acts</hi> 5.21. <hi>Him hath God the Father exalted to be a Prince and a Saviour to give repentance and remiſſion of ſins;</hi> this is plain, Chriſt gives repentance, but how? through faith: Therefore Chriſt muſt firſt be diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red according to the whole tenor of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:102989:16"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> What Prayer is.</head>
            <p>THe glory of man is to underſtand truth diſtinctly without confuſion: Prayer in generall is the going out of the heart to God from a divine diſcovery of a greater good then man hath yet attained.</p>
            <p>Men cannot pray for that which they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend no need of; emptineſſe is the womb that produceth Prayer, and as fire is the cauſe of heat, ſo the ſenſe of a want of God draweth forth the ſpirit to cry after him: Before <hi>Adam</hi> fell, there was no neceſſity of Prayer, for he wanted nothing; neither do I conceive if <hi>Adam</hi> had ſtood Prayer had ever ſprung forth, ſo that we weare it as a badge of our imperfection in this life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> Whether it be the externall voice that makes Prayer? ſome think that no man can be ſaid to pray, unleſſe he ſpeake with his tongue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer: That the externall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery of words cannot be a ſubſtantiall part of Prayer; for if it be, then I may teach a a Parrot to pray: but thus far I acknowledge, that it is the outward forme, and that which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102989:17"/>God hath inſtituted to be amongſt men; for no man can ſay, I pray, unleſſe there be utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and in outward expreſſions another Saint judgeth of my heart, ſo that as to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance, no man can demonſtrate anothers praying, but from the heart to the tongue.</p>
            <p>But let us take heed of confining prayer onely to a way of utterance; for I prove that a Chriſtian may pray, and never ſpeak a word, as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. <hi>The Spirit helps our infirmities with ſighs and groans unutterable:</hi> Sure then the tongue cannot manifeſt what is in a Chriſtian many times when he prayes; for theſe ſighs and groans are the immediate goings out of the heart, which there is a want in words to expreſſe.</p>
            <p>Further, the Spirit ſaith, Pray alwaies, <hi>ſine intermiſſione,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Without any ceaſing,</hi> for ſo the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies; now no man can verbally pray alwayes, for if ſo, then he could have no oportunity to do any other exerciſe: If it ſubſtantially conſiſt in voice, how then ſhall a dumb man pray? ſome were born tongue-tied, yet I hope no man wil ſay they may not pray; ſo likewiſe I would ask how many, or how few words make a prayer, if properly that be any thing as to the ſubſtance, what made the Publicans ſaying,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102989:17"/>
               <hi>God be mercifull to me a ſinner?</hi> there were but ſix words, was it not his heart that made it a Prayer? yea, ſure. Put I conclude this with <hi>Hannahs</hi> Prayer, I <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.12. When, ſhe prav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Eli marked her mouth; now</hi> Hannah <hi>ſpake in her heart, only her lips moved,</hi> he thought ſhe had not prayed, becauſe he heard not her voice, but the Spirit ſaith ſhe prayed; alas! many are not able to ſpeak words as other men can, ſhall we conclude upon that that they may not pray? God doth not ſo much reſpect what words he utters, but with what heart he cries to him; therefore let none ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle out one truth with another, for a Prayer is demonſtrated both wayes, yet I ſay, he that hath the ſpirit of prayer will uſe both, and let no Profeſſor judge prayer only in outward appearance, as the world doth, but judge righteous judgement: This I hint at onely for the comfort of ſome Chriſtians that want words to expreſſe their heart.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:102989:18"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Whether a juſtified perſon may pray for the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin.</head>
            <p>THis queſtion not rightly underſtood, makes a difference of judgements a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, ſome ſaying, we ought to pray for pardon, others we ought not.</p>
            <p>And it may ſeem ſtrange, that one juſtified, pardoned, ſhould after this pray for pardon of thoſe ſins that are already pardoned; this may ſuppoſe Chriſt hath not fully ſatisfied, ſo then the queſtion will be, whether we may pray for pardon of ſuch ſins as are done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by Chriſts death? For I ſay, this is unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably true, that the Father is fully ſatisfied for all the ſinnes of thoſe which believe on him.</p>
            <p>To underſtand this then, I underſtand par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don with this diſtinction, that there is a two-fold praying for the pardon of ſin.</p>
            <p>The one is as to a Judge.</p>
            <p>The other is as to a Father.</p>
            <p>Now the right apprehending theſe two will reſolve the ſcruples.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt then as to a Judge, I may after the manner of men, give this alluſion; God ſits
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102989:18"/>as a Judge upon the Bench to execute Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors: Now for a believer to pray unto God for pardon under this notion, is not according to truth; for I am not now to ſuppoſe God ſits as a Judge to me, and ſo pray, this is only for unbelievers, as I may demonſtrate it by this inſtance.</p>
            <p>The Judge that ſits in the ſeat of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath many malefactors brought before him, he condemns them according to Law.</p>
            <p>Now ſuppoſe it lies in the Judges breaſt to acquit whom he will; he clearing any from the puniſhment, the priſoner is cleared from that fact; now he knowing himſelf freed ſayes no more, <hi>Good my Lord forgive me,</hi> if he doth the Bench will tell him, he is already pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſo bid him hold his peace.</p>
            <p>Now under this notion all men ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God as guilty; now it lies in the heart of the Father to pardon whom he will, when he in Chriſt manifeſts this ſalvation, then the penalty is taken off as to finall Judgement, you will then plainly judge it at leaſt weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in ſuch a man to ſay, Lord forgive me, when he knowes his ſin is pardoned: For this is only a prayer of unbelief at beſt, as <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifies, <hi>Say not in thy heart, who ſhall aſcend into Heaven? this is to bring Chriſt down from above;</hi> that is to ſay, this denies that Chriſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102989:19"/>hath not performed what the Father ſent him to finiſh, this is derogatory to Gods love ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted in his Son.</p>
            <p>But I muſt confeſſe a converted man at firſt by reaſon of miſapprehenſions may pray for a further aſſurance of that pardon, for few men at firſt have full aſſurance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it may be objected, that <hi>David</hi> after converted, prayed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.9. <hi>Blot out mine iniquities;</hi> it ſeems <hi>David</hi> by theſe words thought his fins not all cancelled.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, <hi>David</hi> might thus pray, as not thinking all his ſin was pardoned, but it was father his want of Faith, then that they were not pardoned; and in that <hi>Pſalm</hi> we may read, when <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet came and told him he was the man that killed <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> the ſuddenneſs of the word ſtruck to his heart, and ſo from thence he thought God had not forgiven all his ſin: He ought to have ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed for his going aſide, but not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire.</p>
            <p>Now we are not to ſuppoſe a change in God concerning this act, but onely in our ſelves, as <hi>David</hi> deſcribes the bleſſedneſſe of the man to whom God imputes not ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.7. <hi>And whoſe ſinnes are forgiven and covered:</hi> This word covering is a metaphoricall ſpeech, ſhewing that God looks not now upon us as
<pb facs="tcp:102989:19"/>ſinners, in reſpect of condemnation, but only in Chriſt, and ſo hath fully pardoned and acquitted us from that condemnation that might fall upon us; for we are not to conſider God in this ſenſe, one while forgiving ſin, and another while imputing it to us: And indeed where ever any man that truly believes ſo prayes for ſin to be pardoned, is but a deceit of the Serpent to keep us in continuall fears to think God at one time ſits over us as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, another time as a Judge: For, it is not neceſſary for a Believer to doubt, as many ſay, though I know God hath many ends for our good in that alſo.</p>
            <p>I conclude this particular with this afferti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as before is cleared; That for any Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver once juſtified (<hi>in foro conſcientiae</hi>) to pray for pardon, as to a Judge, not onely makes Chriſts death imperfect, but ſavors ſomthing of Popery, as if I could not be fully ſaved by that ſatisfaction; and I adviſe all that truly beare the name of the Lord, to take heed of Prayers made thus in unbeliefe, for they hereby bring themſelves under the Law of Workes, and hinder the progreſſe of much ſpirituall good in their ſouls.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, there is a praying for the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin as to a Father: Now in this ſenſe my judgement is, that a believer ought to pray for pardon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:102989:20"/>
For want of this diſtinction that is laid down, many (though otherwiſe godly) think they ought not to pray for pardon, and all that they have for it is onely taking pardon but in one ſenſe, and do not diſtinguiſh it.</p>
            <p>But ſome ſuppoſe God ſeeth not ſin in his people, becauſe he is fully well pleaſed and reconciled to us in Chriſt, and ſo if he takes no notice of ſin, then it is our weakneſſe to ask forgiveneſſe of that which God ſeeth not; and for this opinion that place of Scripture ſeems in the letter to favour, <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.21. <hi>He hath not beheld iniquity in</hi> Jacob, <hi>nor tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion in Iſrael;</hi> now we muſt underſtand the ground of this ſpeech, <hi>Balaam</hi> had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved command from God to bleſſe his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and <hi>Balaak</hi> thought that curſing ſhould be pronounced againſt them, therefore this place onely teſtifies that God ſeeth not ſin in his people, ſo as to condemne them, nothing ſhall proſper againſt them, God doth not ſo ſee ſin in them as to cauſe the fruit of ſin to take hold upon them, for there is no inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt Iſrael, they are covered with his garments, therefore freed from all ſuch ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries.</p>
            <p>But I hope none will deny God to be a Father, and though ſin is ſaid to be covered, yet it is abſurd for any to conceive ſin can be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102989:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>carried out of Gods ſight, for he is every where, and ſuch an opinion makes God not omniſcient, and conſequently not God.</p>
            <p>Further, I would ask whether that place be true, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.27. the ſin <hi>David</hi> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted was evill in the ſight of the Lord, now <hi>David</hi> was a Saint in as true a ſenſe as any are, yet God ſaw his evill, and we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not believe but if man may ſee ſinne, God much more.</p>
            <p>But ſome ſay, God may ſee it, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his will, he hath bound himſelf not to ſee it by aboliſhing it out of his ſight, and cloathing us with his righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, God hath in his will determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not to ſee ſinne, ſo as to condemnation and puniſhment: he will not ſo ſtrictly take notice of ſinne in them as in the wicked, in ſuch a capacity, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4.13. <hi>all things are naked and open in his ſight,</hi> that is, not the leaſt things, but the moſt inward and ſecret things of the heart, they are diſſected or ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomized, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) cut up as Chyrurgians doe a creature, to find every vein, or muſcle; thus if God ſeeth ſin, then it makes way to prove that pardon of ſin may be prayed for: Now Chriſt hath not taken away the relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God as our Father by his death, none will judge that true.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:102989:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
What then is the relation of a Father, may not he chaſtiſe his ſon? yea, ſure; as for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, A father that hath one only ſon that is ſole heire to his lands, the ſon ſometimes may croſſe his fathers command, and he may correct him for it, yet he bids ask him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe, and I will not chaſtiſe you, yet the ſon knowes his father cannot diſinherit him for his untowardneſſe.</p>
            <p>Thus God is a father to a believer, who ſomtimes may diſobey a command; now may not God in this relation of a Father in love chaſtiſe his child for good? and though a Saint knowes God will not diſinherit him, yet he will ask forgiveneſſe in this ſenſe; as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Abyſſus peccati invocat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſſum poenae,</hi> one deep calls upon another, the deep of ſin on the deep of puniſhment; but to a Saint I judge that all puniſhment for ſin, according to the terme of the word, is taken away, only a loving correction, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God caſtigates for ſin, or from ſin, I have a latitude in my judgement to ſuppoſe both may be true; and I believe that Chriſt never ſo ſatisfied God, as that he ſhould not correct his people; for Chriſts death did not at all extend to that particular, when Chriſt bad his Diſciples pray, he exhorts them to ſay, <hi>forgive us our treſpaſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:102989:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Now if they need not to ask pardon in this ſenſe, why was this Petition included? ſo it is ſpoken to Saints by the firſt words, ſay, <hi>Our Father;</hi> now in what ſenſe this Prayer may meane we ſhould aske pardon? I anſwer, onely as to a Father, and no otherwiſe; ſo <hi>John, If we confeſſe our ſins, he is faithfull and juſt to forgive us our ſins,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.9. why, was not ſinne for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given before? Yea, in reſpect of juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but this confeſſion and pardon is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly under a fatherly relation: Yet hereby I doe not underſtand, that our Prayers make any change in Gods Will, but rather in praying God doth manifeſt what he will do to us and for us; ſo then I judge that a Chriſtian ought not to pray to God as a Judge for pardon, but may conſider him as a Father.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:102989:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Whether this viſible world ſhall be destroyed, or changed, and how.</head>
            <p>GOD from age to age brings forth ſome old truth as new unto the world; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let not the Reader ſtumble, if he find that here which may at preſent be contrary to moſt mens judgements.</p>
            <p>For that opinion of ſome that ſay the world is judged already in the Saints in ſome reſpect is true, to him that lives in ſpirit; but I will not ſpeak of that, I leave the end to try all things.</p>
            <p>My diſcourſe ſhall only be of this queſtion, Whether this viſible frame of things ſhall be deſtroyed, or changed, which is a great que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion amongſt godly men; which I ſay not that I will reſolve, but only hint at it as the truth is manifeſted in me: Firſt, that this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible world ſhall be deſtroyed by materiall ſire, as ſome places ſeem to allow, as 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7. where the heavens and the earth are kept in ſtore reſerved unto fire, ſome think that as the old world was deſtroyed with water, ſo the Anti-type muſt be like it, that is to ſay, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by fire.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:102989:22"/>
An argument for this opinion may be thus framed.</p>
            <p>Fire is an element ſtrong and fierce, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all matter that is tangible by it may be conſumed, but the viſible world hath matter fit for fire to feed upon, therefore it ſhall be burnt.</p>
            <p>But this argument is more logicall then theological, and it wil not be a hard matter to prove that a great part of the earth, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens is not matter for fire, but rather fights a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
            <p>In the 12. Verſe of the aforeſaid Chapter, the heavens being on fire <hi>ſhall be diſſolved, and the element ſhall melt with fervent heat, that as fire conſumes all ſtubble, ſo there ſhall be an ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſummation:</hi> So in 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.8. he ſhall <hi>come in flaming fire taking vengeance:</hi> ſome from theſe places conclude, that it will be materiall fire, and all things ſhall be burnt up.</p>
            <p>Now to anſwer theſe places, there are ſome Scriptures that ſpeak not of an utter deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and if I erre, conſider with thy ſelf I am not alone.</p>
            <p>I may ask whether thoſe former places ſpeak of fire in a metaphoricall ſenſe, and by way of alluſion and no more; that as the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of fire is to purge and purifie droſſe out of metalls, and it ſuddenly burnes up all
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:102989:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>combuſtible matter, ſo this may note the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denneſſe of that change, and that it will purge the world of its droſſe: And for the <hi>havens melting with fervent heat,</hi> it may point this to us, that they ſhall melt ſo as wax doth by the candle, where it is not deſtroyed, but onely made pliable to receive the impreſſion of the ſcale: ſo the heavens may thus be ſaid to melt, that is to ſay, not deſtroyed, but only changed from thoſe corrupt qualities that are in it, not of the ſubſtance, it ſhall receive the deep impreſſion of Gods image and glory.</p>
            <p>Now to illuſtrate this, that there will only be a change, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Nevertheleſſe we look for a new heaven, and a new earth, wherein dwells righteouſneſſe.</hi> This ſeems to allow, that only the corruption ſhall be taken away, and we ſhall have a new heaven and earth in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. They ſhall be brought forth into a ſtate of purity, freed from bondage, <hi>Non per interitum priſtinorum, ſed commutationem in melius;</hi> not by a deſtruction of the old, but by a change into a better: ſo <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.26. <hi>The heavens ſhall waxe old as a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as a veſture ſhalt thou change them, and they ſhall be changed.</hi> He ſaith not here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:102989:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Now the changing a thing is a converting the ſame to the beſt advantage.</p>
            <p>And the alluſion ſeems to be ſtrange, that as a veſture when changed is not deſtroyed, but onely refined, dreſt, the beſt ſide outward.</p>
            <p>So the world hath at preſent corruption covering it as a garment; therefore it may be tranſlated into a better ſtate: For, if <hi>Davids</hi> words hold true, then it muſt be changed, but not deſtroyed. And indeed the worſt ſide of the world is now outward ſince <hi>Adams</hi> fall.</p>
            <p>But I will not determine whether this change will be by materiall fire, or whether fire in thoſe places be a figurative ſpeech. For the inſtrumentall cauſe of this change, I may have ſome ground to ſuppoſe the contrary, but will leave this to the end which tries all things.</p>
            <p>Some have converted theſe Scriptures into other myſterious ſenſes, and I judge a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all uſe may be made of all things: Yet let none be ſo ignorant as to bind one ſenſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch places as theſe are; for ſome Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures have both a literall and a ſpirituall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning under them.</p>
            <p>For inſtance, where Chriſt is ſaid to raiſe the dead, cleanſe the lepers, heal the ſick, and the like, no man can truly deny but that CHRIST did fulfill this in the letter:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102989:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>yet he doth it in a ſpirituall ſenſe: alſo every man hath <hi>Microcoſmos, Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 3.11. a little world in him: Now God in order to the great change; begins firſt in mans heart, therefore let Chriſtians take heed of denying one truth by binding it to another: For to avoid error I would take ſuch Scriptures in the largeſt ſenſe, for both theſe meanings may be in few words.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP, VI.</hi> Whether all creatures ſhall be restored to their priſtinate ſtate in <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE whole Creation ſince <hi>Adams</hi> fall hath been ſubject to innumerable evills and changes: Now ſome are of opinion that all creatures ſhall be reſtored, excepting ſuch as are for the food and cloathing of man, and they give this reaſon, becauſe man ſhall have no need then of ſuch helps, but ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
            <p>I anſwer: By the ſame rule all creatures ſhall not be reſtored; for every creature in its kind doth conduce to the life of man, as might be made eaſily to appeare: For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever concurres to life may be called food and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:102989:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>cloathing; ſo that if any creature may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from this liberty by the former opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then all may.</p>
            <p>But doth not that place teſtifie that all ſhall not be reſtored, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 60.19. <hi>The Sun ſhall be no more light by day, nor the Moon give light unto thee, but the Lord ſhall be thy everlaſting light.</hi> I might give a ſpirituall ſenſe of theſe words, but ſhall only anſwer as to the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; it ſeems by this place that the Sun and Moon ſhall be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>I anſwer: The Prophet ſpeaking of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious appearing of God, intimates all ſuch lights ſhall be darkened as we have walked in without himſelfe: But if it may be litterally underſtood, then mark the words, he ſaith not the Sun and Moon ſhall be no more, but they ſhall give light no more; that is to ſay, their light ſhall be no more in reſpect of that profit man hath had by them, for God ſhall be our light, our ſtate will be beyond the creatures perfection, much leſſe ſhall we want their light: Yet they may be, though we have no benefit by them, as no man is ſo blind in judgment as to ſay the Sun is not, becauſe it is under a cloud; and as the greater light ſwallowes up the leſſe, ſo this teſtifies onely that the light of God will ſwallow the light and luſtre of all excellencies, as to our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:102989:25"/>yet they may ſtill be. So then I judge there will be a reſtauration of all things, and thoſe words witneſſe it <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.21. <hi>The creature it ſelf was made ſubject to vanity, and it ſhall be delivered from the bondage of corruption into the glorious liberty of the ſons of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now then the bondage of the creature what is it, but a ſubjection to corruption? Look then what liberty the ſons of God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, the ſame all creatures are to have; but it is <hi>in ſuo modo,</hi> in their kind, or according to their nature: I ſay not a part of the creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but the whole creation (or every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) groans for the <hi>manifeſtation of the ſons of God.</hi> And although they have not a ſenſe of liberty, yet they have of miſery: ſo <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21. mentions a time when there muſt be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of all things. Now if the whole creation hope for that which they ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver attain to, why are thoſe Scriptures menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned ſo fully to this point?</p>
            <p>Therefore I conclude, that there will be a generall reſtauration: but whether they ſhall be reſtored to the ſtate in <hi>Adam,</hi> or more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, I will not fully determine: yet ſuppoſe it will be a more glorious perfection.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:102989:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> When, or about what time will this change be?</head>
            <p>THis queſtion being more difficult then neceſſary, I may not ſearch into the time, holding it godly wiſdome to be ignorant of it; yet many men have weakly betrayed their wiſdome in ſpending much time upon this particular.</p>
            <p>I will onely hint at ſome probabilities that divers have ſuppoſed about it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, there were many Jewes got an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion from one <hi>Elias</hi> a man eminent amongſt them, who ſaid, that as the world was made in ſix dayes, and the ſeventh God reſted, ſo the world ſhould ſtand ſix thouſand years and no longer, and ſtrengthened his opinion upon 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. <hi>One day with God is a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, and a thouſand years one day,</hi> and thus taking a day for a thouſand years, ſix dayes make ſix thouſand; but alas, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered not the ground of this expreſſion, which <hi>Peter</hi> onely uſeth to confute the ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of thoſe dayes, that thought God was far enough off, he condemns their ſecurity, and informes them time is nothing to eternity.</p>
            <p>A ſecond ſort were ſuch as by Arethmetical
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:102989:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>numbers, as by a witty invention calculated the time, as one did out of two words, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fLagratIo M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nDl,</hi> finding ſo many numeral letters in theſe words as make up 1657. from thence concluded, that in that year the world muſt end; and to hold up this opinion, they ſay <hi>Noahs</hi> flood was in 1657.</p>
            <p>So others, as <hi>Picus Mirandula,</hi> ſaid it ſhould end in 1905. And formerly in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many divers went about, ſaying, in ſuch a year it muſt end: As I have read one <hi>Thoda</hi> a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in Germany in 848. went about ſtreets and told people that ſhe had it from an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, that the world ſhould end that yeare, whereby many became prodigall of their goods, fearing they ſhould not ſpend them in ſo ſhort a time. Others more moderately divide the world into ſix Ages, and ſay the ſeventh Age the end muſt be; the Ages are thus divided.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, from the Creation to the Flood.</item>
               <item>Second, from the Flood to <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Third, from <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>David.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fourth, from <hi>David</hi> to the Captivity.</item>
               <item>Fifth, from the Captivity to Chriſt.</item>
               <item>Laſt, from Chriſt to the end of the world; ſo that the beginning of the ſeventh age will be the full reſtauration: And as <hi>Enoch</hi> was the ſeventh from <hi>Adam,</hi> and was tranſlated,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:102989:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>for God took him; ſo this may be a figure of this ſtate, that the ſeventh Age God ſhall be fully manifeſt: This opinion my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment leads me to believe neareſt to truth; for certainly this is the laſt age, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. witneſſeth.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Now to ſuch as will deſcant upon time, to ſhew their learning, I will leave them to learne what thoſe words meant, <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.32. <hi>But of that day and hour knoweth no man, no not the Son, ſave the Father.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> What ſure ground we have to believe this change is nigh.</head>
            <p>ALthough I am againſt ſuch as prefix a time to this change, yet as great men ſend Harbingers before them to give notice of their coming; ſo God hath divers meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers that proclaime this coming.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt is the unſealing of the Scriptures, God reveals not all at once, as time ſhuts up, truth opens, God hath truth for ſeverall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; <hi>Daniel</hi> was bid to <hi>ſeale up the book till the end, Dan.</hi> 12.4. the nearer the end is, the more open will ſuch truths be as concerne
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:102989:27"/>the end; God will not draw his curtains ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly open, not ſhew all at once, <hi>men ſhall run to and fro, and knowledge ſhall increaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, this intimates an inquiſition in people after the Lord; they ſhall inquire the way to Zion with their faces that way: as ſnow ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by rowling, ſo truth ſhall mightily increaſe by going to and fro, the nearer the Iudge is, the more the people run and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire when he comes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to and fro notes the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of fellowſhip amongſt brethren, they ſhall run to and fro, backwards as well as forwards, not to this friend, or that friend, but to back friends as well as boſome-friends, there will be no reſpect of perſons in this ſenſe: this notes his coming nigh who is him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe no reſpecter of perſons: The poor and the rich will be one with a knowing ſoule, the language will not be, I will go to the rich mans houſe; no, the rich hath many friends, but the poor are deſtitute. When a houſe is on fire, men ſay not I will ſtay at home, becauſe I am rich, or an Officer, but all run to quench the fire; ſo when there is a fire of an inlightened underſtanding kindled, then we ſhall ſee Saints go to a <hi>Lazarus</hi> as well as to a <hi>Dives:</hi> Knowledge is much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved in theſe days, I wiſh it be as well pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:102989:27"/>
2. The ſecond note is, the coldneſſe of love amongſt Profeſſors: Many ſhall be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table quench-coales in this laſt age: Honeſt <hi>Latimer</hi> ſaw love ſo cold in his time, that he thought Dooms-day at hand: But alas, how dead are Profeſſors now in love! And the reaſon is, becauſe mens affections are placed upon Opinion, and not upon practice: Such a man is of my opinion, therefore I love him; this is ſelf-love: Lord, what a helliſh fire will this kindle! May not a man be thy brother, and yet not like thee in all things?</p>
            <p>I would ask all Profeſſors this queſtion, What is it you love in one another? Is it the form, or the power of god lineſſe? One part divides from another, becauſe they are not in way, or that way of worſhip: But conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, this is not Chriſt all, and in all?</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe none ought to be ſo ignorant as to ſay, A man is the leſſe a Chriſtian, becauſe he is not of the Presbyterian Church ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; neither is he the leſſe a Chriſtian, becauſe he is not of the Independent Church ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. If you all hold the Head, you are of one myſticall Body, and I hope will meet one day meet together as the <hi>generall Aſſembly and Church of the firſt-born, whoſe names are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in heaven, Heb.</hi> 13.23.</p>
            <p>Have fellowſhip then in the ſpirit of truth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:102989:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>and uprightneſſe. <hi>Baſil</hi> complains of his time, That he ſaw more union in Arts and Sciences, then in Divinity, by reaſon of thoſe conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that were amongſt brethren. For, men in diſputes rather diſpute for ſelf, then truth: Pride will not let men ſubmit, though con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience tells them they ſpeak againſt truth. This coldneſſe of love demonſtrates the change not far off.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third note is, the working of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.24. Men uſually admire a thing done beyond their capacity; ſuch works have naturally a great force upon mans fancy: As the Jewes require a ſigne, ſo the zealouſly ignorant ſhall mightily follow and adore ſuch men.</p>
            <p>Many there are that out of weakneſſe of judgment think there can be no preaching, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Apoſtles did work miracles.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, that miracles were not in any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree eſſentiall to make a Miniſter: For, the Apoſtles might preach without them; onely God was pleaſed to uſe them, for the firſt planting the Goſpell: And although ſome may expect miracles in theſe laſt times, which I confeſſe muſt come to paſſe, yet I know no place that mentions, that God will ſend any of his people that ſhall work them, but rather they ſhall be falſe Prophets, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.22. te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:102989:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>The Papiſts in their Legend of lies tell the People, that they are the true Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they work miracles; but they are lying miracles.</p>
            <p>Signes are only for unbelievers, and the Kingdom of Heaven cometh not by obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Such then as will not believe untill they ſee miracles wrought, I may ſay to them as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> to <hi>Dives, Luke</hi> 16.31. <hi>They have Moſes and the Prophets, if they will not heare them, neither will they believe, though one roſe from the dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that where working of ſuch miracles are, it is a ſigne of a falſe Prophet; and I will never follow a man the more, becauſe he may have this gift.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth note is, when the Goſpell is going through the whole world, <hi>Mark</hi> 13.10. And ſurely God is beginning much in this work to gather his Saints together: More in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments God wil raiſe for this purpoſe, then ever were ſince the world began: For, we ſee God is breaking down thoſe Lawes and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions that hindred many men from this glorious work: But I will not abſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the ſeverall wayes God uſeth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert men: For, a man may be converted by the reading ſome Scriptures, or by ſome thoughts of God; that is in a ſenſe a preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:102989:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>to the heart, when God ſpeaks within him, ſaying, <hi>this is the way, walk in it:</hi> Sure I am that the Goſpell ſhall run and be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The fifth note is, when the fire of love goes out, then the fire of perſecution comes in; the brother ſhall betray the brother: the nearer Antichriſt is to his end, the greater will be his rage: And this muſt come to paſſe: For, I obſerve, the more zealous any man is for form then power, the greater perſecutor will ſuch a people be, when authority is on their ſide. The reaſon is, Becauſe ſuch men do it out of conſcience to God. <hi>Paul</hi> was the greateſt perſecutor we read of among the Jewes: <hi>The time ſhall come when men that kill you ſhall think they do God good ſervice, Iohn</hi> 16.2.</p>
            <p>He that is born after the fleſh will perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute him that is born after the ſpirit: <hi>Iſhmael</hi> will trouble <hi>Iſaac.</hi> God hath pulled, down one horn of this Antichriſt, I pray God we may not ſee a ſharper riſe in its ſtead, when the face of Religion is onely waſht, but not the heart; an outward reformation, but an inward deformation: <hi>Ier.</hi> 9.4. <hi>Then truſt not in a brother, for he will utterly ſupplant:</hi> it is hardeſt to reconcile brethren, for love cauſeth jealouſie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:102989:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
When you ſhall ſee the abomination of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation [<hi>Mat.</hi> 24.15.] ſtanding where it ought not: ſurely there is no place where abomination ought to ſtand: This alludes to Jeruſalem, a place where Chriſt and his Diſciples had preached, they offered ſacrifice, but to their own nets, made a ſhew of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, yet under it acted abomination, perſecu-and injuſtice.</p>
            <p>I pray God it, may not be ſo with thee, O England, to be a profeſſing people, talk of holy walking, yet in this holy place to act wickedneſſe, injuſtice, oppreſſion, ſelf-ſeeking and covetouſneſſe, to make Religion a skreen to all irreligious practiſes; this is an iniquity to be puniſh'd by the Judge: How abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is it for one man, to pretend his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours good, yet under that notion to take his lands and livings over his head? Many men make uſe of Religion as a ſtirrup to get a horſe-back into the worlds preferments; Lord! whether will that man run, horſe, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and all to deſtruction! Such men have Gods cenſure, you eat my people as bread, to ſhew thy ſelfe as if thou wouldſt feed Gods people, yet under it act ſuch abomination as is odious to all; as the fiſher baits his hook with meat for the fiſh, when he intends onely to make the fiſh meat for himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:102989:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
This is ſuch an abomination which God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to pull downe in all, as he hath moſt gloriouſly begun this work, ſo come Lord, is the language of a true Iſraelite, throw it down in me and every one.</p>
            <p>The ſcarcity of upright, unbiaſſed hearts notes the end nigh; a reall friend like Chriſt who ſhall find, to prevent this miſchiefe that may juſtly come upon us? I adviſe all that profeſſe the name of the Lord in ſincerity, however they are called or diſtinguiſhed by the corrupt man, that they would love all that be are their fathers image, though it be ſmall, not for form ſake, but for godlineſſe ſake, love the truth as it is in Jeſus, not as this man, or the other man ſpeaks it, and untill this be, for my part I believe diviſions will increaſe, which is the rode way to perſecution. Mark the words of <hi>James, Pure Religion and undefiled before God and the Father, is this: To viſite the fatherleſſe children, and widdowes, and to keep your ſelves unſpotted from the world,</hi> J am. 1.27.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:102989:30"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Whether we may not expect a glorious rest before this finall appearing, and what reſt it will be.</head>
            <p>GLorious things are ſpoken of this laſt age, and divers opinions there are about it; ſome conceive a perſonall reign of Chriſt, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.3.4 <hi>They lived and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand years;</hi> but I underſtand this ſpiritually that he ſhall reign in them, not as he was upon earth, as ſome dream, for <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21. ſaith,<hi>the heavens muſt retain him til the time of restitution of all things:</hi> Some thinke this thouſand years began at his birth, others at his Reſurrection, there being books extant on this ſubject, ſhall not ſpeak more of this; for to me I find not the leaſt ground of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall reign of Chriſt: when he went away, he never ſaid, I will come a gaine perſonally, but <hi>I will ſend my Spirit that ſhall lead you into all truth,</hi> not that I will come again in fleſh upon earth, and live a thouſand years, but in Spirit; and in that place it is ſaid, <hi>they lived and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand years,</hi> but it ſaith not upon earth, for there is no ſuch word.</p>
            <p>But I muſt truly ſay, there will be a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:102989:31"/>reſt for the Saints in divers particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
            <p>As firſt, in powring out the Spirit, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.8. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.17. <hi>In thoſe dayes I will powre out my Spirit on all fleſh, your ſons and daughters ſhall prophecie,</hi> you ſhall not ſay one to another know the Lord, for you ſhall be all taught of God; this promiſe in my judgement hath this meaning in it, that we ſhall no longer reſt in men, ye ſhall not need that any man teach you, man with his principles, parts, learning: you ſhall no longer ſay to this man, or that man, teach us, for ye ſhall all be taught of God, you ſhall be brought off from that ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh opinion in the world, that think none but men learned in Arts can teach, no my Spirit that ſhall teach you, ye ſhall then come to acknowledge Gods teaching in all, for ye ſhall be made to confeſſe, that it is not <hi>Paul, Apollo,</hi> nor <hi>Cephas,</hi> but Chriſt in ail that tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth: this promiſe doth not overthorw the preaching of the Goſpell, as ſome men may judge, but is a comparative ſpeech, ſignifying what knowledge ſhall be in theſe laſt times, and no man ſhall therefore believe a thing true, becauſe the Miniſter ſaith ſo, but they ſhall have a ſpirit of underſtanding given to know things, as 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.27. declares to us, that <hi>as the ſame anoynting teacheth us,</hi> ſo we ſhall
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:102989:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>judge whether it be God or man that ſpeaks, and thoſe weak words ſhall be laid aſide, as we now ſay, ſuch and ſuch a man taught me, this is a deſtroying thy Maker; therefore thou ſhalt ſay, <hi>It was the Lord, and I knew it not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have many times admired why Chriſtians get ſo little by hearing, and I find the cauſe to be this: they go to hear men and not God, and ſo they divide; if you be not taught of God to love another, you can never learn it of men: Alas! man is but the cane in which ſugars lies, the trunk through which God ſpeaks; man is but <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> a voice and no more; this will be a bleſſed time when we ſhall give every thing its due, not ſay ſuch a man can teach me more then another, this is a calling upon <hi>Malcham,</hi> to make ſome King or Ruler over thee, beſides the true God; <hi>Call no man therefore your Maſter,</hi> (or Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher) <hi>but one even God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, there will be much love and quietneſſe amongſt people; the Lion ſhall eat ſtraw like the Oxe, the Wolf ſhall dwell with the Lamb, they ſhall not hurt, nor deſtroy in all my holy mountain: Theſe are metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall expreſſions, to note God will mightily reſtraine the ſpirits of men; what a wonder is it to ſee a Wolfe lie quiet with a Lamb? ſo it will be, all Lion-like devouring, tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:102989:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>proſecuting ſpirits ſhall be as a Lamb, made ſtill, and ſtirre nor, God will turn Lions into Lambs, great abominable ſinners into gracious Saints: Knowledge ſhall cover the earth, as waters cover the Sea; that is, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively to former times: Men ſhall be filled with this divine wiſdome, the fool ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the wiſe, the weak the mighty, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 2.4. <hi>They ſhall beat their Swords into plow ſhares,</hi> what ever was as a ſword to kill, deſtroy lives, liberties of one another, that ſword ſhall be turned into a plow ſhare, it ſhall now worke for the good of all: this notes to us abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of peace that will be in mens ſpirits; no more cries or perſections ſhall be heard in our ſtreets, the time is coming that perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall ceaſe, <hi>Mic.</hi> 4.5. <hi>All people will walk every one in the name of his God, and we will walk in the name of the Lord our God;</hi> all ſuch Lion, and Wolviſh ſpirits ſhall be taken a-away.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, for an outward peace how far that will extend, take a few hints: That cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly tyranny ſhall be abated much, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice ſhall run down like a river; <hi>Eſa.</hi> 32.18. <hi>The people ſhall dwell in quiet habitations;</hi> and <hi>ſhall ſit every man under his vine and his fig tree and none ſhall make them afraid, Mic.</hi> 4.4. No power outward or inward ſhall diſmay them,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:102989:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it: the abundance of corrupt Lawyers ſhall be pulled down, and when that is done, then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, O ye inhabitants of the earth, for Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, or confuſion and deceit is falling, and untill this be done, we muſt expect no fulfilling of juſtice to run as a river: we have ſome ſtreames already, but thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers ſtop the currents they are ſuch as darken caunſell, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.52. keep the <hi>key of Knowledge,</hi> and by that gaine wedges of gold to themſelves, and <hi>Diana</hi> muſt down in all. To performe this worke, God faith, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.26. <hi>I will reſtore unto you Rulers as at the firſt, and Judges as at the beginning;</hi> God ſits now a refining and gives us great hopes of Judges and Rulers, hating cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe and ſelfe-ends; there muſt be ſuch as are like <hi>Melchiſedeke,</hi> to know no kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred or friend, when in Authority for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get all relations, but doe juſtice to all without reſpect to this or that friend, <hi>Levit.</hi> 24.22. <hi>There ſhall be one manner of Law as well for the ſtranger as the countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man:</hi> The Law ſhall be plaine, eaſie, let corrupt men ſeek what they can to hinder it, the ſtranger ſhall know it, he that hath no learning, as well as he that hath; the ſame to the poor as to the rich.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:102989:33"/>
So from all this I ſay not that the Saints ſhall have only an earthly glory, grow high, and they onely poſſeſſe the high places of the earth; but my judgement is, that there ſhall be a ſweet moderation in Government: and though we cannot expect all in Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhould be Saints, yet man (though car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall) ſhall have a ſpirit for the liberties of the People, and ſhall deal juſtly.</p>
            <p>Now when God will accompliſh this worke he hath promiſed, I may not fully conclude, but ſay it ſhall be wrought within theſe few yeares; for I ſee God is coming to throw downe oppreſſion, injuſtice, tyranny, in all powers on earth, and he hath already laid the way and foundation for this worke in theſe laſt eight years; therefore rejoyce O ye people, for God is delivering you from thoſe outward bondages.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:102989:33"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> A teſt of divine Joy, and what that joy is.</head>
            <p>DIvine Joy ariſeth from a ſight of, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the moſt glorious object: Now in the working of joy it is neceſſary, that there be a union, to and with the object, for no man can delight in that which he neither knows nor affects: and indeed theſe two are the wings of the ſoule that heighten this joy.</p>
            <p>Now in the order of joy, theſe two things much aggravate it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Contemplation in the mind of man, fixed upon the object; for every man, by a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and ſolid meditation of what the affects, hath a various delight in him, according to the nature of the object.</p>
            <p>Therefore God, by way of expreſſion as to us, did not ſo much rejoyce in his <hi>fiat,</hi> as in his <hi>vidit,</hi> not ſo much when he gave all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures a being, as when he ſaw their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and he had much delight in his works made, becauſe in them he beheld his own I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and glory.</p>
            <p>A ſoul thus beholding God, as one with him in Chriſt, being taken with the object, the thoughts of God are ſweet to him, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:102989:34"/>I thought of thee in the night ſeaſon, and it was ſweet to me;</hi> for ſerious meditation carries this ſoul ſometimes in a rapture above it ſelf; and when a Saint comes to apprehend their infinite good in God, he is ſwallowed up in himſelf, and all fears are vanquiſhed in him, and is as <hi>Paul</hi> whether in the body, or out of the body he can not tell; <hi>Paul</hi> had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got his former ſtate by the preſent purſuit of his deſire, and overflowing of his affections towards that immortall good he ſaw, he had forgot himſelf, and had a new ſelf. Thus the ſoule when filled with joy, all its former fears are buried in the preſent joyes, as <hi>Jacob</hi> when he heard his ſon <hi>Joſeph</hi> was alive, his great fear of the loſſe of <hi>Benjamin</hi> was at preſent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome by that joy he had of <hi>Joſephs</hi> ſafety: Thus a ſoul, when touched with the loadſtone of the Spirit, is drawn up into a greater joy and glory. Joy in this ſenſe makes death light and ſmall in a Chriſtians eye; for ſuting of en object oppoſite to death, which is life, and by this beats out the diſmall apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of it, and with <hi>Paul</hi> 'cries, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting?</hi> As Mariners when they come to land, make a ſhout to note their joy of a ſafe arrivall; ſo the ſoul by divine joy is carried from the ſea of earthly confuſion, and arrives ſafe into the land of Canaan, where
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:102989:34"/>his joy is unexpreſſible: thus divine Joy comes through the underſtanding, and works much upon the other faculties: This we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in all men, that according to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, ſo commonly is their joy or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light; for the mind of man feeds upon his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, as the Bee ſucks ſweetneſſe from the flower, as a worldly man his mind, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently delight is moſt upon his riches.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond aſſiſtant to joy is hope, or confidence in the mind, whereby a man waits for the accompliſhment of his deſires; as a man in priſon inferrs joy to himſelf from that hope he hath of liberty; for indeed hope doth enlarge joy, by carrying us from our preſent fears, to our future joys, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.12. <hi>Rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in hope;</hi> this quickens our preſent joy by hope of a more full joy; for confidence addes ſtrength to the weak, and courage to the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſo hope drawes in joy as the loadſtone doth thee needle; <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Rejoyce in hope of the glory of God:</hi> it makes abſent things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and we feed upon thoſe joyes that are to come; now beſides thoſe grounds of joy there are others that much widen it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, the ſudden and unexpected ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of any good to us ſurprizeth the ſoul with much joy, as the long departure of a dear friend, his return to us not looked for,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:102989:35"/>or expected, cauſeth more joy, then if he had given notice of his coming.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of this is, becauſe they ſurprize us, and ſo ſtir up that affection in us more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly. Sudden joy hath ſo wrought upon ſome bodies, that they have died pleaſantly in the midſt of their joyes. I knew a man in Chriſt two years ago that was carried up in ſpirit into the heaven of joy, that at preſent he wiſht he might die inſtantly, to go to that bleſſed fellowſhip. Some have been ſo tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported beyond themſelves, that they have forgot their worldly buſineſſe, and were as men loſt to reaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond is ſtrength of deſire: For, ſtrong deſires are never at reſt untill they are ſatiated with the object of their deſire: For, deſire is like a woman with child, never qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted till ſhe obtains what ſhe longs for.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Darius</hi> in his flight drank muddy water, he profeſſed he never found greater pleaſure in his drinking, becauſe the appetite of thirſt being ſtrong, was much delighted where it met with a ſatisfaction. Thus the ſoul of a Chriſtian having ſtrong deſires in her, ſhe never reſts till ſhe in joyes the object of her deſire: For indeed a man can never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in that which he hath no deſire after. <hi>Proverbs</hi> 13.19. <hi>Deſire accompliſhed is ſweet
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:102989:35"/>to the ſoule:</hi> it brings much joy and comfort to a Saint when his deſires are fulfilled: As the Hart pants after the water brooks, ſo doth the ſoul after God.</p>
            <p>And truly the ground why a Chriſtian hath ſo little joy is, becauſe he hath not the ſtrength of deſire, and is not yet drawn by a divine power to thirſt after the living God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third is imagination. Imaginati-in in man is either the foundation of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light or ſorrow; Conception of any good in things moves delight in them: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when <hi>Diogenes</hi> in his melancholy fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie took more delight in his tub, then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men do in their palaces: For, the fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie loves to feed upon ſome quaint thing diſtinct: And as imagination works, it binds the heart to a delight in whatever it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives pleaſant. Divine joy moves in the ſame manner as earthly joy doth, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pitcht upon a higher object. Theſe two wayes divine joy manifeſts it ſelf to us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, union is the principall conduit-pipe through which this joy proceeds. A ſoul uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Lord hath all from him. What an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean of joy coms into the ſoul, with that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriating title, <hi>God is mine!</hi> For all true joy flowes as naturally from this, as the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:102989:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>river runs from the Sea; and indeed the cauſe of mans miſery in earth ariſeth from a not-knowing himſelf united to the Lord by one Spirit; for this union is much more glorious then any relation on earth, and carries all ſweetneſſe and delight with it: The knot of union is tied ſo ſtrong by divine love, that what ever is Gods pleaſure, can never be a Saints paine, propriety gives life to a cauſe, when a ſoul can ſay, God and all in him is mine, and for me, what joy do you think it will produce?</p>
            <p>Then ſecondly, poſſeſſion adds much to a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine joy; thus faith doth give the ſoul a poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of him, who poſſeſſeth all things; untill a man hath poſſeſſion in his own lands, he can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fully rejoyce: for this aggravates my joy, when I have ſo much as at my command. Good old <hi>Simeon</hi> when he had imbraced Chriſt in the arms of faith, then for joy deſired to die, that he might fully poſſeſſe him: Thus a ſoul when injoying Chriſt in the arms of faith, his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes are gone, what joy was there for the loſt Prodigall when he was come to his Fathers houſe? As in outward delights thoſe of incorporation are better then thoſe of adheſion; ſo inward joyes they are ſtrongeſt, becauſe they proceed from a fruition of good, not a ſpeculative apprehenſion: Now God
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:102989:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>is ſuch an infinite eternall good, that the ſoul is united to him; joy by this dilates and opens the heart, whence it is called <hi>Latitia,</hi> which ſignifies joy to be a ſpreading paſſion, for the object is ſo univerſally good and ſweet, that divine joy cannot be bound, but runs out freely to this glorious object; and there can be no locking up of divine joy, but it runs forth as the father to meet the loſt Prodigall: The nature of this joy (as one ſaith) is like the water of <hi>Eſculapius</hi> his well, which is not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of putrifaction. This I am ſure of, where the ſoule joyes in God, there can no poiſon mix with it, and there can be no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in this delight, for heaven is its proper title, which ſignifies a Kingdome of Joy; <hi>At thy right hand are pleaſures for evermore:</hi> Now the excellency of divine joy further appears in two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, it beholds life in eternity, for in all naturall things joy doth ariſe from ſome kind of life or motion.</p>
            <p>Eternall life is the womb of divine joy, that firſt brought it forth, and is the nurſe that feeds it and ſtrengthens it: Therefore when the ſoule rightly underſtands that it ſhall live with the Lord, the ſpirit is exalted to ſatiate it ſelf upon life; on the contrary, take a man that knowes not this life, for the moſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:102989:37"/>part, when he comes to die, he is ſad, deſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, for death naturally produceth ſorrow as life doth joy.</p>
            <p>Therefore, <hi>there ſhall be more joy in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at the converſion of one ſinner, then of nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty nine that need no repentance;</hi> to intimate unto us, that the joy of a dead man raiſed to life is much increaſed by the difficulties it met with in conquering death.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, Divine joy tranſports the ſoul beyond a fear of ſuffering; nay, the ſoul thus ſet upon glory, rejoyceth in tribulation it ſelfe, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.11. Therefore the Saints of old rejoyced that they were counted worthy to ſuffer: Now affliction is an evill not to be deſired; yet conſidering the event all ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, that they make way for a greater glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, thus a Saint in divine joy ſees to the end of all ſufferings: And as a woman in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail forgets her pains, for joy that a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child is born into the world; ſo divine joyes ſnatches up the ſoule above all earthly bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. As ſome Martyrs ſung in the fire, M. <hi>Philpot</hi> ſaid, the world wonders how we can be ſo merry in ſuch miſery, but they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider not that God turneth our miſeries into felicitie. So <hi>Vincentius</hi> laughing at the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures laid upon him, ſaid, they were his <hi>Jocula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria &amp; Ludicra,</hi> matters of ſport and paſtine to him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:102989:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Now another reaſon why Saints joy in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, is Chriſt went as a patterne before us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Who for the joy that was ſet before him indured the Croſſe, deſpiſed the ſhame:</hi> Old <hi>Latimer</hi> tells us, that it's the greateſt promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion God gives in this world; thus a ſoul in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine joy calls death no more <hi>Marah,</hi> but <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A man in heavenly joy, we may ask him, <hi>quid agis?</hi> but may as well draw in all the breath of the world, as tell what a Saint is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, not that there is want of words, but want in words to expreſſe it: Therefore it is called unſpeakable joy, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. not but that we may ſpeak of it, but we cannot deſcribe the dimenſions of this joy.</p>
            <p>Thus far of the nature of divine joy.</p>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>An incouragement to joy in the Lord.</head>
               <p>AS a bird while priſoned in a cage, ſings little and dolefully, but when ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in the open aire, it ſings ſweetly; ſo a Saint is in a cage of an uncleane world, where his joy is but ſparkling, but when in the open aire of Gods ſweet Kingdome, then the ſoule will ſing ſweetly, as the ſingers of Iſrael. Rejoyce then in hope, O my ſoule, let thy winter ſeaſons be paſt over
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:102989:38"/>with delight, For thy ſummer is nigh. Art thou afraid of death? Look into the land of the living, and tell me, is not death ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in victory? Art thou afraid of men? why behold, (<hi>Colloſ.</hi> 3.3.) thy <hi>life is hid with Chriſt in God,</hi> lock'd up as a Jewell in a Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket: Art thou afraid of finne, doth that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der joy? The ſting of death which is ſinne, is taken away, Chriſt hath fully ſatisfied the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for thee; death is but life growing out of it; ſorrow is joy in its ſeed budding forth; ſufferings are but ſo many leſſer Crownes breaking forth into greater glories: Why ſhould not a Saint rejoyce in all ſtates? look on thy Saviour, haſt thou not cauſe to joy in him?</p>
               <p>While I thus beheld the God of Love, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, what's the world to me! In its ſmiles, frownes, deaths contradictions, I compare it thus:</p>
               <p>It is as a picture drawne out by a curious Artiſt, where it is not one colour makes the image comely, but all the colours, the black as well as the white line, the red as well as the blew, that makes it delectable: Thus all in the world is but a connexion of colours, take all together they make a ſweet harmony; then O ſoul rejoyce, and know that all things work for thy good, the dark part as well as
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:102989:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>the bright part of things; whileſt thy joy is in the Lord, then in every thing thou meeteſt with, thou meeteſt with a pleaſure, for thy God doth all things well; delight thy heart in the Lord, if Satan hurt thy ſoule vvith his bloud-hounds, fly to the rock of Gods love, thou art ſafe; fly in all thy diſtreſſe by this wing of love, to love: A Saint filled vvith joy flies to heaven aforehand, and hath the ſvveet fellowſhip of Gods Angells, ſpirits of juſt men, in this bleſſed work of joy: <hi>Paul</hi> was thus rapt up to the third heaven; O the ſweet, glorious, divine, everlaſting, ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, viveficating, ſoul-filling, ſpirit-ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, unknown, yet well known joys of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry! thy joy O earth! is but as the crackling of thorns: thou art droſſy, frothy, frenzy in thy joy, all thine is but imaginary conceited joy. A Chriſtian ſees that every thing is but borrowed in the world, time will challenge all ſuddenly: the great man, rich man, noble man, voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, covetous man, time will challenge you all; then whoſe are your honours, riches, pleaſure, profits? all die with you; but bleſſed are ſuch as partake of divine Joys: I onely can point at this joy, but cannot paint it out to you: Therefore <hi>rejoyce in the Lord alway, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, I ſay, rejoyce,</hi> Phil. 4.4.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
